Hey folks, where we left off I was
talking about how to compute a
three-dimensional cross product between
two vectors, V cross W.
It's this funny thing where you write a
matrix whose second column has the
coordinates of V, whose third column has
the coordinates of W, but the entries of
that first column, weirdly, are the
symbols I hat, J hat, and K hat, where
you just pretend like those guys are
numbers for the sake of computations.
Then, with that funky matrix in hand,
you compute its determinant.
If you just chug along with those
computations, ignoring the weirdness,
you get some constant times I hat plus
some constant times J hat plus some
constant times K hat.
How specifically you think about
computing that determinant is kind of
beside the point. All that really
matters here is that you'll end up with
three different numbers that are
interpreted as the coordinates of some
resulting vector.
From here, students are typically told
to just believe that the resulting
vector has the following geometric
properties.
Its length equals the area of the
parallelogram defined by V and W.
It points in a direction perpendicular
to both V and W. And this direction
obeys the right-hand rule, in the sense
that if you point your forefinger along
V and your middle finger along W, then
when you stick up your thumb, it'll
point in the direction of the new
vector.
There are some brute-force computations
that you could do to confirm these
facts, but I want to share with you a
really elegant line of reasoning.
It leverages a bit of background though,
so for this video I'm assuming that
everybody has watched chapter five on
the determinant and chapter 7 where I
introduce the idea of duality.
As a quick reminder, the idea of duality
is that anytime you have a linear
transformation from some space to the
number line, it's associated with a
unique vector in that space in the sense
that performing the linear
transformation is the same as taking a
dot product with that vector.
Numerically, this is because one of
those transformations is described by a
matrix with just one row where each
column tells you the number that each
basis vector lands on.
And multiplying this matrix by some
vector V is computationally identical to
taking the dot product between V and the
vector you get by turning that matrix on
its side.
The takeaway is that whenever you're out
in the mathematical wild and you find a
linear transformation to the number
line, you will be able to match it to
some vector, which is called the dual
vector of that transformation. So that
performing the linear transformation is
the same as taking a dot product with
that vector.
The cross product gives us a really
slick example of this process in action.
It takes some effort, but it's
definitely worth it.
What I'm going to do is define a certain
linear transformation from three
dimensions to the number line and it'll
be defined in terms of the two vectors V
and W.
Then, when we associate that
transformation with its dual vector in
3D space, that dual vector is going to
be the cross product of V and W.
The reason for doing this will be that
understanding that transformation is
going to make clear the connection
between the computation and the geometry
of the cross product.
So, to back up a bit, remember in two
dimensions what it meant to compute the
2D version of the cross product?
When you have two vectors V and W, you
put the coordinates of V as the first
column of a matrix and the coordinates
of W as the second column of a matrix.
Then you just compute the determinant.
There's no nonsense with basis vectors
stuck in a matrix or anything like that,
just an ordinary determinant returning a
number.
Geometrically, this gives us the area of
a parallelogram spanned out by those two
vectors with the possibility of being
negative depending on the orientation of
the vectors.
Now, if you didn't already know the 3D
cross product and you're trying to
extrapolate, you might imagine that it
involves taking three separate 3D
vectors U, V, and W and making their
coordinates the columns of a 3x3 matrix.
Then computing the determinant of that
matrix.
And as you know from chapter five,
geometrically, this would give you the
volume of a parallelepiped spanned out
by those three vectors with a plus or
minus sign depending on the right-hand
rule orientation of those three vectors.
Of course, you all know that this is not
the 3D cross product.
The actual 3D cross product takes in two
vectors and spits out a vector.
It doesn't take in three vectors and
spit out a number. But this idea
actually gets us really close to what
the real cross product is.
Consider that first vector U to be a
variable, say with variable entries X,
Y, and Z
while V and W remain fixed.
What we have then is a function from
three dimensions to the number line. You
input some vector XYZ and you get out a
number by taking the determinant of a
matrix whose first column is XYZ
and whose other two columns are the
coordinates of the constant vectors V
and W.
Geometrically, the meaning of this
function is that for any input vector
XYZ, you consider the parallelepiped
defined by this vector V and W. Then you
return its volume with a plus or minus
sign depending on orientation.
Now, this might feel like kind of a
random thing to do. I mean, where does
this function come from? Why are we
defining it this way?
And I'll admit, at this stage it might
kind of feel like it's coming out of the
blue. But if you're willing to go along
with it and play around with the
properties that this guy has, it's the
key to understanding the cross product.
One really important fact about this
function is that it's linear.
I'll actually leave it to you to work
through the details of why this is true
based on properties of the determinant.
But once you know that it's linear, we
can start bringing in the idea of
duality.
Once you know that it's linear, you know
that there's some way to describe this
function as matrix multiplication.
Specifically, since it's a function that
goes from three dimensions to one
dimension, there will be a 1 by 3 matrix
that encodes this transformation.
And the whole idea of duality is that
the special thing about transformations
from several dimensions to one dimension
is that you can turn that matrix on its
side and instead interpret the entire
transformation as the dot product with a
certain vector.
What we're looking for is the special 3D
vector that I'll call P such that taking
the dot product between P and any other
vector XYZ gives the same result as
plugging in XYZ as the first column of a
3 by 3 matrix whose other two columns
have the coordinates of V and W, then
computing the determinant.
I'll get to the geometry of this in just
a moment, but right now let's dig in and
think about what this means
computationally.
Taking the dot product between P and XYZ
will give us something times X plus
something times Y plus something times Z
where those somethings are the
coordinates of P.
But on the right side here, when you
compute the determinant, you can
organize it to look like some constant
times X plus some constant times Y plus
some constant times Z.
Where those constants involve certain
combinations of the components of V and
W.
So those constants, those particular
combinations of the coordinates of V and
W are going to be the coordinates of the
vector P that we're looking for.
But what's going on on the right here
should feel very familiar to anyone
who's actually worked through a cross
product computation.
Collecting the constant terms that are
multiplied by X, Y, and by Z like this
is no different from plugging in the
symbols I hat, J hat, and K hat to that
first column and seeing which
coefficients aggregate on each one of
those terms.
It's just that plugging in I hat, J hat,
and K hat is a way of signaling that we
should interpret those coefficients as
the coordinates of a vector.
So what all of this is saying is that
this funky computation can be thought of
as a way to answer the following
question.
What vector P has the special property
that when you take a dot product between
P and some vector XYZ, it gives the same
result as plugging in XYZ to the first
column of a matrix whose other two
columns have the coordinates of V and W,
then computing the determinant.
That's a bit of a mouthful, but it's an
important question to digest for this
video.
Now for the cool part which ties all
this together with the geometric
understanding of the cross product that
I introduced last video.
I'm going to ask the same question
again, but this time we're going to try
to answer it geometrically instead of
computationally.
What 3D vector P has the special
property that when you take a dot
product between P and some other vector
XYZ, it gives the same result as if you
took the signed volume of a
parallelepiped defined by this vector
XYZ along with V and W.
Remember, the geometric interpretation
of a dot product between a vector P and
some other vector is to project that
other vector onto P, then to multiply
the length of that projection by the
length of P.
With that in mind, let me show a certain
way to think about the volume of the
parallelepiped that we care about.
Start by taking the area of the
parallelogram defined by V and W,
then multiply it not by the length of
XYZ, but by the component of XYZ that's
perpendicular to that parallelogram.
In other words, the way our linear
function works on a given vector is to
project that vector onto a line that's
perpendicular to both V and W, then to
multiply the length of that projection
by the area of the parallelogram spanned
by V and W.
But this is the same thing as taking a
dot product between XYZ and a vector
that's perpendicular to V and W
with a length equal to the area of that
parallelogram.
What's more, if you choose the
appropriate direction for that vector,
the cases where the dot product is
negative will line up with the cases
where the right-hand rule for the
orientation of XYZ, V, and W is
negative.
This means that we just found a vector P
so that taking a dot product between P
and some vector XYZ is the same thing as
computing that determinant of a 3 by 3
matrix whose columns are XYZ, the
coordinates of V and W.
So, the answer that we found earlier
computationally, using that special
notational trick, must correspond
geometrically to this vector.
This is the fundamental reason why the
computation and the geometric
interpretation of the cross product are
related.
Just to sum up what happened here, I
started by defining a linear
transformation from 3D space to the
number line, and it was defined in terms
of the vectors V and W.
Then, I went through two separate ways
to think about the dual vector of this
transformation. The vector such that
applying the transformation is the same
thing as taking a dot product with that
vector.
On the one hand, a computational
approach will lead you to the trick of
plugging in the symbols I hat, J hat,
and K hat to the first column of a
matrix and computing the determinant.
But thinking geometrically, we can
deduce that this dual vector must be
perpendicular to V and W with a length
equal to the area of the parallelogram
spanned out by those two vectors.
Since both of these approaches give us a
dual vector to the same transformation,
they must be the same vector.
So, that wraps up dot products and cross
products. And the next video will be a
really important concept for linear
algebra, change of basis.